Hi everybody. Today's דף Daf is י"א, Yud Aleph, eleven. We're a
little behind, but let's, this is going to be focused, we can
maybe, God willing, we will catch up. So we start at the
very last line of י'
עמוד א'. Yud Amud Aleph. תניא: Tanya: מכוונות לדרכים. Mekhovanot la'derakhim. So
in the middle of the creating of the ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat,
and it says that they would, you know, have the paths all
leading to it. In the משנה, Mishna, it sounds like the paths
would interconnect the various ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, which is not the
most useful. What you really want are paths leading from all places
in the land to the ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. You know, what
is it? All roads lead to Rome, all roads lead to ערי
מקלט. Arei Miklat. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. תני
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר: Tani Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer: מקלט
היה כתוב על פרשת דרכים. Miklat haya katuv al parashat drakhim. At
the all the crossroads, there would always be a sign saying מקלט
Miklat this way. Okay, very helpful, right?
Throughout the country, anytime you got to crossroads, Yogi Berra says, when
you come to a fork in the road, take it. Right? So
anyway, so at all the crossroads you would always know exactly which
way to turn to get to the ערי מקלט Arei Miklat כדי
שיכיר הרוצח ויפנה לשם, kedei she'yakir ha'rotzeach ve'yifneh lesham,
so he should be able to see and turn that way. Again,
it's very interesting that all this, this person who killed בשוגג beshogeg
is consistently referred to as רוצח. rotzeach. אמר רב כהנא: Amar Rav
Kahana:
מאי קרא, mai kra, what's the verse that says you have to
do this? תכין לך
הדרך, takhin lekha ha'derekh, prepare the way. What does it mean, prepare
the way? עשה לך הכנה לדרך, aseh lekha hakhana la'derekh, make the
way, you know, directed and make the way prepared so that it's
easy for him to get there.
You also have to do road maintenance, too.
That's a good point. Road maintenance is a good point. רב חמא
בר חנינא פתח לפתחא להאי פרשתא מהכא. Rav Chama bar Chanina patach
le'pitcha le'hai parshata mehakha, So when רב חמא בר חנינא Rav Chama
bar Chanina was going to דרשן darshen on the discussion of the
ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, he would be פותח הפתיחתא, poteach ha'ptichta, begin
his opening from the following. And this, by the way, is a
classic form of rabbinic מדרש. Midrash. You see it throughout מדרש רבה,
Midrash Rabbah, like בראשית רבה, Bereishit Rabbah, שמות רבה, Shemot Rabbah, the
פתיחתא, ptichta, which is that you usually open from a different פסוק
pasuk and then you find your way to get to, you know,
like if you're talking about פרשת תולדות, Parshat Toldot, you say like
what is it? עטרת זקנים בני בנים ותפארת בנים אבותם, ateret zekenim
bnei banim ve'tiferet banim avotam,
whatever it is. You know, what is it?
ותפארת בנים אבותם. ve'tiferet banim avotam.
And then you say as well, and then, you know, so and
that you use that to open and then that's going to be
your, and then you somehow you're going to get to the story
of אברהם Avraham and יצחק. Yitzchak. You know, so anyway, so here
too the idea is how would you, what would you do your
פתיחתא ptichta from? Where would be the פסוקים pesukim that you would
start from in order to wind your way, excuse the pun, anyway,
to get your way over to the discussion of ערי מקלט. Arei
Miklat. So רב חמא בר חנינא Rav Chama bar Chanina פתח לפתחא
להאי פרשתא מהכא, patach le'pitcha le'hai parshata mehakha.
so he would begin it from here: טוב וישר ה' על כן
יורה חטאים בדרך. tov ve'yashar Hashem al ken yoreh chata'im baderekh.
God is right and just and therefore He will show the sinners
the path. So obviously the point here is somebody who's a sinner,
again, similar to call רוצח, rotzeach, there was negligence led to the
death, it's not a complete accident, and nevertheless God wants to create
the paths in order to protect the sinners and help them get
to the ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. And then the דרשה drasha was,
if for חטאים, chata'im, קל וחומר kal vachomer to צדיקים. tzaddikim. If
this is what He does for the wicked, how much more so
to the sinners, how much more so for the righteous? ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish פתח לפתחא להאי פרשתא מהכא. patach le'pitcha le'hai parshata mehakha.
He would open the פתיחתא ptichta from the following place: ואשר לא
צדה והאלוהים אינה לידו. ve'asher lo tzadah ve'ha'elohim ina leyado. Now this
is actually starting straight with the פסוק. pasuk. It's not starting from
a distant פסוק pasuk or some פסוק pasuk in תנ"ך Tanakh and
נ"ך Nach and moving your way, it's starting straight in the פרשה.
parsha. He would jump straight in. Okay. Now, but here's the פסוק
pasuk that would be a little off-topic that he would weave in:
כאשר יאמר משל הקדמוני מרשעים יצא רשע, ka'asher yomar meshal ha'kadmoni me'resha'im
yetze resha,
like the early, sort of, you know, parables, thank you, משל הקדמוני,
meshal ha'kadmoni,
from wicked people comes out evil. So apparently רש"י Rashi says what's
bothering him is, you know, in this פסוק pasuk is אלוהים אינה
לידו, elohim ina leyado,
that God made it happen. So it sounds like God made this
person's death happen and the person who killed him was just God's
כלי, kli, you know, was just the means and God wanted this
to happen. So if God wanted this to happen and God caused
it all to happen, why does this guy have to go into
exile? That's the problem, אלוהים אינה לידו. elohim ina leyado. So the
answer is מרשעים יצא רשע, me'resha'im yetze resha,
evil comes from bad people. This person was evil to begin with,
and that's why even though God is manipulating the whole thing, but
ultimately this person goes into exile because he was evil to begin
with. How do we understand what that means? So he says במה
הכתוב מדבר, bameh hakatuv medaber, what does the verse refer to? בשני
בני אדם שהרגו את הנפש, bishnei bnei adam she'hargu et hanefesh, two
people who committed murder or killed. אחד הרג בשוגג, echad harag beshogeg,
one did it unintentionally, ואחד הרג במזיד, ve'echad harag bemezid,
and one did it willfully. ולא היו עדים לזה ולא היו עדים
לזה, ve'lo hayu edim leze ve'lo hayu edim leze, neither one have
witnesses. So they both got off scot-free. One's a real murderer, the
other has committed manslaughter, and they both got off scot-free. So what's
God going to do? הקדוש ברוך הוא מזמינם לפונדק אחד, HaKadosh Baruch
Hu mazminam le'pundak echad,
God made the events happen so that they both wind up coming
to the same inn. זה שהרג במזיד יושב תחת הסולם, ze she'harag
bemezid yoshev tachat hasulam, and the one that killed intentionally sits under
the ladder. murder is sitting under a ladder, וזה שהרג בשוגג יורד
בסולם, v'zeh she'harag b'shogeg yored ba'sulam, and the one that's killed unintentionally
is going down a ladder. Notice has to be going down, remember
that. ונפל עליו והרגו, v'nafal alav v'harago, and fell on him and
killed him. So every justice is served. זה שהרג במזיד נהרג, zeh
she'harag b'meizid neherag, the one who committed who killed willfully is killed
as he would have been executed in a court, וזה שהרג בשוגג,
v'zeh she'harag b'shogeg, the one who killed unintentionally, גולה, goleh, goes exile
as he should have been done for his first act. So therefore
God made it happen, but ultimately justice is being served and the
guy who goes in exile on the one hand he was a
כלי klei of God and on the other hand ultimately this is
what he had deserved anyway.
I mean I think it's worthwhile to point out, yes, because looking
up in the context of מרשעים יצא רשע, me'resha'im yeitzei rasha, it
is in the context of David and Shaul how, you know, David
saying I could have killed you Shaul but I'm not going to.
Right.
So it's about murder and
whatever and not doing it and not the right.
Okay thank you. אמר רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב הונא ואמרי
לה אמר רב הונא אמר רב אלעזר, amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna
amar Rav Huna v'amrei lah amar Rav Huna amar Rav Elazar, מן
התורה מן הנביאים מן הכתובים, min haTorah min haNevi'im min haKetuvim, we
learn out from Torah, Nevi'im, and Ketuvim, בדרך שאדם רוצה לילך בה
מוליכין אותו, b'derech she'adam rotzeh lalechet bah molichin oto, in the path
that somebody wants to go with God, you know, they make it
possible in heaven or they send you on the path that you
anyway were going. Okay מן התורה דכתיב לא תלך עמהם, min haTorah
d'chtiv lo telech imahem, by Bilam
it says do not go with them, and then Bilam insists, so
since Bilam keeps on nudging God, God says וכתיב קום לך אתם,
v'chtiv kum lech itam, fine you want to go, go. Okay that's
בדרך שאדם רוצה לילך, b'derech she'adam rotzeh lalechet, you want to go
so God lets you go, God is not going to stand in
your way. מן הנביאים דכתיב אני ה' אלהיך מלמדך להועיל מדריכך בדרך
תלך, min haNevi'im d'chtiv ani Hashem elohecha m'lamdecha l'ho'il madrichacha b'derech telech,
I
am God your God teach you for benefit, I
I guide you in the path that you will go. So the
way it's being read is not I guide you in the path
that you should go, but in the path that you anyway wanted
to go I will help guide you there so, you know, if
you want to go do evil I'll make it possible I'll, you
know.
But then we have the whole thing
about לפני עור lifnei iver though like? Well it's mostly this is
that God isn't standing in your way. מן הכתובים דכתיב, min haKetuvim
d'chtiv, ומצאו גואל הדם והרגו, u'metza'o go'el hadam v'harago, I'm sorry
I skipped a line. דכתיב אם ללצים הוא יליץ ולענוים יתן חן,
d'chtiv im laleitzim hu yalitz v'la'anavim yitein chein,
if with the mockers God will be mock and but for the
for the, you know, for the humble God will be gracious. Now
what does that show? So Rashi says it means אם ללצים, im
laleitzim, if somebody who wants to go ahead and be a mocker
or, you know, do evil, הוא יליץ, hu yalitz, God will make
it possible for him to do so. So God is not going
to stand in the way. Okay God will, so this is of
course the idea of דרך, derech, פותחין לך, potechin lach, this guy
is trying to run to the עיר מקלט ir miklat and the
Torah's making it possible for him to do so but now we're
obviously using that as a metaphor and also, you know, in terms
of also bad stuff that God is not going to stand in
the way of somebody who wants...
Not only is he not standing in his way, he's telling him
to go though which is a little bit different. Where? Bilam. לך
אתם. lech itam. He's telling him to go.
He's giving him permission I don't know. Anyway if you look at
Rashi הוא יליץ, hu yalitz, אין מעכבין בידו. ein me'akvin b'yado. Okay
אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, רוצח שגלה לעיר מקלט, rotze'ach she'galah
l'ir miklat, ומצאו גואל הדם והרגו, u'metza'o go'el hadam v'harago, פטור. patur.
Now we're going to get into some הלכה. halacha. So the guy
is running to the עיר מקלט ir miklat and the גואל הדם
go'el hadam kills him on the way. Okay is he already protected
when he's on the way? So he says the גואל הדם go'el
hadam is exempt until he makes it to the עיר מקלט, ir
miklat, he's exposed, he's not protected by law. Okay פטור, patur, כסבר
ולו אין משפט מות, kasavar v'lo ein mishpat mavet, right? וגואל הדם...
v'go'el hadam... וגואל הדם הוא
דכתיב.
u'v'go'el hadam hu
d'chtiv.
Okay so the פסוק pasuk says, right? That this person will go,
you know, to the city to the ערי מקלט, arei miklat, and
it says פן ירדוף גואל הדם אחרי הרוצח, pen yirdof go'el hadam
acharei harotze'ach,
lest the avenger of blood run after the murderer, אחרי הרוצח כי
יחם לבבו והרגו בדרך, acharei harotze'ach ki yeicham levavo v'harago baderech, ולו
אין משפט מות,
v'lo ein
mishpat mavet, right?
ולו אין
משפט
מות,
v'lo ein mishpat
mavet, we have to create ערי מקלט arei miklat lest the גואל
הדם go'el hadam runs after him and kills him on the way,
ולו אין משפט מות כי לא שנא הוא לו מתמול שלשום, v'lo
ein mishpat mavet ki lo sonei hu lo mitmol shilshom, and he
doesn't deserve to die because he didn't hate him from the past.
So the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is that the one
who killed the person doesn't deserve to die because it was an
unintentional death. Okay and the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is
now is it now the פסוק pasuk is seems to be saying
we're creating the ערי מקלט arei miklat to prevent the גואל הדם
go'el hadam from killing him on the way. So it seems to
say that he's protected on the way, right? And therefore we have
to he has to be protected on the way lest the גואל
הדם go'el hadam runs after him and kills him. But this way
is reading it: no, if the גואל הדם go'el hadam succeeds in
killing him on the way, ולו אין משפט מות, v'lo ein mishpat
mavet,
the גואל הדם go'el hadam is not liable for having killed that
person, okay, because he got him before he got to the עיר
מקלט. ir miklat. And since the גואל הדם go'el hadam will be
exempt before he gets to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, you have
to תכין לך הדרך, tachin lacha haderech, you have to make sure
that the guy can get to the עיר מקלט ir miklat as
quickly as possible. That's a pretty I mean the problem with... That's
a pretty—I mean, the problem ולא שנא לו מתמול שלשום v'lo sanei
lo mitmol shilshom doesn't fit so well because that's clearly talking about
the guy who did it, but it's a very reasonable read of
the verse, which is this גואל הדם Goel HaDam could kill him
before he gets to the ערי מקלט Arei Miklat and get away
with it. So you have to do everything you can to make
sure he gets to the ערי מקלט Arei Miklat as quickly as
possible. So that's what he says. ולא אין משפט מות v'lo ein
mishpat mavet ובגואל הדם הוא דכתיב. u'v'goel hadam hu dichtiv. That's referring
to the גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, he's not liable. מתיבי, Masevei, I
ask you, ולא אין משפט מות v'lo ein mishpat mavet ברוצח הכתוב
מדבר. berotzeiach hakatuv medaber. We have a ברייתא braita that says that's
talking about the one who killed the guy. Okay, אמרת
ברוצח או אינו אלא בגואל הדם, Amarta berotzeiach o eino ela b'goel
hadam, maybe it's referring to the גואל הדם Goel HaDam that he's
not liable while the guy's on the way, כשהוא אומר והוא לא
שנא לו מתמול שלשום, kshehu omer v'hu lo sanei lo mitmol shilshom,
he didn't hate him from the past, הוי אומר ברוצח הכתוב מדבר.
hevei omer berotzeiach hakatuv medaber.
That's clearly talking about the guy who killed him and saying that
it was unintentional because he didn't hate this guy who died.
He says it twice, והוא לא שנא לו.
v'hu lo sanei lo. I understand. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
you see according to this ברייתא braita it's not said about the
גואל הדם. Goel HaDam. So נו, nu, הוא דאמר, hu de'amar, this
position goes like the one that says, כי האי תנא ki hai
tanna like the following תנא tanna דתניא, Detanya, ולא אין משפט מות
v'lo ein mishpat mavet בגואל הדם הכתוב מדבר. b'goel hadam hakatuv medaber.
There's a תנא tanna that says it is referring to the גואל
הדם, Goel HaDam, that he's not liable if he kills the guy
on the way. אתה אומר בגואל הדם הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא
ברוצח, Ata omer b'goel hadam hakatuv medaber o eino ela berotzeiach, maybe
it's referring to the murderer or the killer, כשהוא אומר כי לא
שנא לו מתמול שלשום, kshehu omer ki lo sanei lo mitmol shilshom,
the end of the פסוק pasuk לא שנא לו מתמול שלשום lo
sanei lo mitmol shilshom is totally ironic.
That is clearly talking about the guy who killed and that he
is and that he's not sort of, you know, to be treated
as a murderer, he did not do it intentionally. So since that
last phrase is talking about the guy who killed, the previous phrase,
ולא אין משפט מות v'lo ein mishpat mavet would be redundant if
it was talking about the guy who killed. So the previous phrase
ולא אין משפט מות v'lo ein mishpat mavet clearly is talking about
the גואל הדם Goel HaDam according to this.
Does he think there's a different, has a better interpretation of this?
Of the גמרא? Gemara? Yeah, the way... Okay, one minute, let me
finish reading it. או אינו אלא ברוצח כשהוא אומר כי לא שנא
הוי רוצח אמור. o eino ela berotzeiach kshehu omer ki lo sanei
hevei rotzeiach amur. הא מני מקיים ולא אין משפט מות בגואל הדם
הכתוב מדבר. Ha mani mekayem v'lo ein mishpat mavet b'goel hadam hakatuv
medaber. So it's talking about the גואל הדם. Goel HaDam. So we
have this very critically important debate whether when the תורה Torah says
he is not liable for death, is it referring to the one
who's running away and that he's protected while he's running to the
עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, or does it mean that the גואל הדם
Goel HaDam won't be liable for death, and because of that you
have to make—you have to ensure that this guy can get to
the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat as quickly as possible.
Yes, because I think what the גמרא Gemara is trying to say
is because in פסוק ד' pasuk daled you have וזה דבר הרוצח
אשר ינוס שמה וחי אשר יכה את רעהו בבלי דעת והוא לא
שנא לו מתמול שלשום. v'zeh devar harotzeiach asher yanus shamah vachai asher
yakeh et re'ehu bivli da'at v'hu lo sanei lo mitmol shilshom. Right.
So that first part is clearly רוצח. rotzeiach. Maybe it says later.
Oh, so you mean the והוא
לא שנא לו v'hu lo sanei lo in that first part is
talking about the רוצח. rotzeiach. Maybe. Could be. He said it later,
okay, so it's the same one we're talking about before. So that's
the first opinion, that it's talking about the רוצח. rotzeiach. Second one
is, no, since you already talked about the רוצח rotzeiach in the
first part, the second time it's already talking, it's talking about different
גואל הדם. Goel HaDam.
I hear, I hear. Okay. So it's that the הוי לא שנא
לו hevei lo sanei lo is going about the earlier reference to
that. That could be. Okay. Let's go on.
Anyway, you have this critical debate whether the person is protected on
the way. I actually think פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, although
ולא שנא לו v'lo sanei lo and ולא אין משפט מות, v'lo
ein mishpat mavet, I do think פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim
is referring to the guy who killed, but I think that the
idea that the גואל הדם Goel HaDam can kill him with impunity
until he gets to the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat is פשט pshat
of the פסוקים, psukim, and that's why the פסוקים psukim say תכין
לך הדרך. tachin lcha haderech. You've got to make sure because lest
the guy,
he's exposed before he gets to the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat.
So he needs some תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim.
Exactly. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is now going to deal
with. Okay, תנן. Tnan. So now let's see if we can sort
of figure this out based on a
משנה. Mishnah. תנן, Tnan, מוסרין לו שני תלמידי חכמים שמא יהרגנו בדרך
וידברו אליו. mosrin lo shnei talmidei chachamim shema yehorgeno baderech v'yedabru elav.
So you have these two תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to talk to
the גואל הדם. Goel HaDam. So מאי לאו, mai lav, what are
they going to say to him? So if they're תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim presumably the reason is to talk הלכה. halacha. So they're דמסתברי,
demistabri, they'll give him הסברה hasbara דאי קטל בר קטלא הוא, de'i
katel bar katla hu, and tell him if you kill this guy
you're going to be liable to the death penalty. So that's why
you need תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. This proves that the person is
protected along the way, and that's what the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
are there to do, is to tell the גואל הדם Goel HaDam
that he's protected and that he could, he would be committing murder.
So לא, lo, no, maybe it just means that they'll be just
persuasive, maybe it does not mean they're going to talk הלכה. halacha.
לא, Lo, I understand. כדתניא, Kedatanya, וידברו אליו דברים הראויים לו, v'yedabru
elav dvarim hara'uyim lo, you speak to him things that he's able
to hear. אומרים לו אל תנהג בו מנהג שופכי דמים, Omerim lo
al tinhag bo minhag shofchei damim, hey, don't kill this guy, don't
treat him like a murderer.
בשגגה בא מידו, Bishgaga ba miyado, the whole thing was an accident.
Okay, and of course as Mike says, good luck with that with
a גואל הדם Goel HaDam who's running in his heat of passion
and you say to him, oh you know it was just an
accident. Okay, and why do you need תלמידי חכמים? talmidei chachamim? But
maybe the גמרא Gemara assumes that תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, maybe they
have a certain authority to them, you know, maybe they can speak
in a certain like nuanced way. Okay, but yes, this is the
issue. Are they telling him הלכה, halacha, hey you should know the
guy is protected, you'll be committing murder, or are they just trying
to persuade him? Okay, רבי מאיר אומר הוא מדבר על ידי עצמו.
Rabbi Meir omer hu medaber al yedei atzmo. He's even, he can
even or should even, could even talk for himself. שנאמר וזה דבר.
shenemar v'zeh devar. The word of the רוצח. rotzeiach. אמרו לו, amru
lo, so the rabbis said back to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, הרבה
שליחותו עושה. harbeh shelichuto oseh. You know what? Having somebody speak for
you, having an emissary can accomplish a lot that you can't accomplish
yourself. So it was very important, especially if you're trying to defend
your own life and saying, "Hey, you know, here's the guy who
killed, you know, your relative," and he's trying to convince you not
to kill him. Right? It's probably not going to be so successful,
okay? So it's often very helpful to have an intermediary rather than
to try to do it yourself.
So anyway, so this is a הלכה halachic debate. אמר מר, Amar
Mar, בשגגה במצא לידו. bishgagah b'matsa leyado. So what they say to
the גואל הדם goel hadam is, "Hey, you should know this was
just an
accident." פשיטא, Peshita, דבמזיד בר גלות הוא? d'vemezid bar galut hu? Obviously,
because otherwise, דבמזיד בר גלות הוא? d'vemezid bar galut hu? Obviously this
was an accident because if it was intentional, you think the guy
would be going to
the עיר מקלט ir miklat and be protected?
Right. The point is, it's not like you're an intellectual point that
you're making with the גואל הדם, goel hadam, it's a persuasion point.
Okay?
But the גמרא Gemara says if it's במזיד, b'mezid, so the guy...
Yeah, that's also true.
He wouldn't want to go to the עיר מקלט.
ir miklat. Well, that's the גמרא's Gemara's answer. The גמרא Gemara says,
"אין, in, yes." Maybe the גואל הדם goel hadam thinks that this
guy is a מזיד. mezid. And maybe they actually are not just
persuading the גואל הדם, goel hadam, but informing him that he's a
שוגג. shogeg. Why? דתניא, Detanya, because we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
everybody goes to the עיר מקלט ir miklat initially. So it could
be he's running to the עיר מקלט ir miklat and he is
a
מזיד. mezid. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda omer,
בתחילה אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד מקדימין לעיר מקלט. batchila echad shogeg v'echad
mezid makdimin l'ir miklat. You send everybody to the עיר מקלט. ir
miklat. ובית דין שולחין ומביאין אותם משם. U'veit din sholchin u'mevi'in otam
misham. And בית דין Beit Din then, you know, they take control
of the whole thing and then they recall the people from the
עיר מקלט. ir miklat. It's like a jail. מי שנתחייב מיתה הרגוהו.
Mi shenitchayev mita hargu-hu. The person who then is executed, who is
found guilty of murder is executed, שנאמר ושלחו זקני עירו ולקחו אותו
משם ונתנו אותו ביד גואל הדם ומת. shene'emar v'shalchu ziknei iro v'lakchu
oto misham v'natnu oto b'yad goel hadam vamet. Of course, the פשט
pshat of those פסוקים psukim is the גואל הדם goel hadam kills
him, so there's still some maintenance of the vigilante justice under the
control of בית דין. Beit Din. But of course, that's not הלכה
halachah what we do. The בית דין Beit Din executes him. מי
שלא נתחייב פטרוהו. Mi shelo nitchayev patru-hu. If somebody was completely innocent,
you know, is either total אונס ones or maybe he didn't even
do it, so then they just free him, שנאמר והצילו העדה את
הרוצח מיד גואל הדם. shene'emar v'hitzilu ha'edah et harotzeiach miyad goel hadam.
They free him. מי שנתחייב גלות, Mi shenitchayev galut, and the person
who killed but it was
בשוגג, bishgagah, מחזירין אותו למקומו, machzirin oto limkomo, שנאמר והשיבו אותה העדה
אל עיר מקלטו אשר נס שמה. shene'emar v'heshivu otah ha'edah el ir
miklato asher nas shamah. Okay, so basically, so yes, part of the
thing the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim have to do is not just
persuade but also inform. You should know this guy, yes, it's true
he killed your brother or whatever, but it was an accident.
Wait, so they say it all the time then, even if he's
a מזיד, mezid, right? Well, they say it all the time?
No, I don't think that you have the תלמידי חכמים... talmidei chachamim...
it's a good point, but I don't think you have the תלמידי
חכמים... talmidei chachamim... you send the guy to the עיר מקלט. ir
miklat. But how are they going
to know if he's a מזיד mezid or a שוגג? shogeg?
Well, if there's no תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, then you can... No,
but how do the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim know? Yeah, that I
was wondering too. You have to have like a presumption of what
happened before you actually have the court case. I do understand. I
assume the case is that anytime בית דין Beit Din thinks that
there's, you know, that thinks that it could be a שוגג, shogeg,
they would tell him it's a שוגג. shogeg. But I was wondering
the same thing.
Yeah, is it before it went to court or was it a
מזיד? mezid? Then he wouldn't be able to run to the...
No, this is what before it's gone to the court. ראובן Reuven
killed שמעון. Shimon. Okay?
Now he runs to the עיר מקלט ir miklat to wait until
the trial.
Yes, as he's running to the עיר מקלט ir miklat to wait
until the trial, the גואל הדם goel hadam is running after him.
So Michael says, "Okay, how do the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim know
to tell the גואל הדם goel hadam he's a שוגג shogeg not
a מזיד mezid since we haven't had the trial yet?" So I
assume though that they would say based on the presumption of what
we know right now, or if it looks like it's possible it
was a שוגג, shogeg, that's what they would tell him.
Instead of going to trial?
That does not... but that's not what the ברייתא braita says. The
ברייתא braita says they tell him, "Hey, don't kill him, he was
a שוגג." shogeg. You know? Of course, the question is that would
they, you know... It's an interesting question as well, which I thought
Michael was asking, which is, would they also want to say
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to protect even the מזיד mezid guy? Well,
that's the question. Right, because you want, still, you want the court
to deal with it, you don't want the גואל הדם goel hadam
to deal with it. Okay, so anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, מאליהן הן גולין. me'aleihen hen golin.
Now רבי Rebbi said, "No, no, no. That's not...
that's not the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. The פשט pshat
of the פסוקים psukim is not that בית דין Beit Din sends
the מזיד mezid to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Yes, the פסוקים
psukim do say explicitly that the בית דין Beit Din will send
to the עיר מקלט ir miklat to get the guy to come
and then they'll execute him if he did it במזיד. b'mezid. So
the פסוקים psukim do describe a scenario where a מזיד mezid guy
went to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. But רבי Rebbi says that
was not under בית דין's Beit Din's authority. The guy just ran
on his own to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. If בית דין
Beit Din is controlling it, then the מזיד mezid guy they'll just
keep like, you know, I don't know, local to the court, maybe
some jail in the court or whatever they'll do, but he won't
go to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Okay, so when the מזיד
mezid goes to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, that was his own
decision. מאליהן הן גולין. Me'aleihen hen golin. כסבורין הן, Kasvorin hen, אחד
שוגג ואחד מזיד קולטת. echad shogeg v'echad mezid koletet.
They think, the ones who killed במזיד, b'mezid, that the עיר מקלט
ir miklat protects a person whether they're שוגג shogeg or מזיד. mezid.
ואינן יודעים שבשוגג קולטת ובמזיד אינה קולטת. V'einan yodim she'bishgagah koletet u'vemezid
einah koletet.
But actually it does not protect the intentional murderer. So here you
have a fascinating debate of how to read the פסוקים, psukim, and
it seems like it's also... debate about whether is the guy who
killed במזיד b'meizid protected as long as he's in the עיר מקלט
ir miklat until the trial can be held or does the גואל
הדם goel hadam able to enter into the עיר מקלט ir miklat
and kill the guy who killed במזיד b'meizid and get off scot-free?
Of course, as Michael points out, the whole question is how do
you determine whether the גואל הדם goel hadam what he did was
right or not right and whether the עיר מקלט ir miklat was
protecting or not protecting if you haven't had the trial yet? Maybe
have the trial after the guy's already, after the רוצח rotzeach is
already dead. I don't know, it's...
but then he can't defend himself.
I understand. It's very
strange, I agree. Okay. אמר רב אלעזר עיר שרובה רוצחים אינה קולטת.
Amar Rav Elazar, ir sherubu rotzchim aina koletet. Let's say your עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, you know, your עיר מקלט ir miklat is supposed
to be, I said a minute ago jail, but I only meant
that it was functioning that way in the interim, but obviously from
the earlier גמרא Gemara we see that you have a vibrant city.
It's not a huge city, a vibrant town. And one of the
functions it does is it serves as a sanctuary city. Okay. But
if it happens that everybody in the town, or a majority of
the people in the town, as he says, these people who killed
בשוגג, beshogeg, it stops functioning. Okay? You need sort of the normal
people to give it a status of a town that then protects
the minority population that are the, that are the, that are the
people who killed. שנאמר ודיבר באזני זקני העיר ההיא את דבריו, shenemar
v'diber b'oznei ziknei ha'ir hahi et devarav, this is in יהושע Yehoshua
where it talks about the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, and he'll speak
in the ears of the elders of that city. ולא שהושוו דבריו
לדבריו, v'lo shehushevu devarav l'devarav, it means that they are distinct from
him, from the guy who committed murder. They're not like they're all
in the, in the same category. ואמר רב אלעזר עיר שאין בה
זקנים אינה קולטת. V'amar Rav Elazar, ir she'ein ba zekenim eina koletet.
If there are no elders, it doesn't work. דבעינן זקני העיר וליכא.
d'ba'inan ziknei ha'ir v'leka. These פסוקים psukim in יהושע Yehoshua tell us
the criteria of what you need for an עיר מקלט ir miklat
and you need there to be elders. איתמר עיר שאין בה זקנים.
Itmar, ir she'ein ba zekenim. Now this is actually debated. רב אמי
ורב אסי. Rav Ammi v'Rav Assi. חד אמר קולטת, chad amar koletet,
one says it still protects, וחד אמר אינה קולטת, v'chad amar aina
koletet, it doesn't. מאן דאמר אינה קולטת בעינן זקני העיר, man d'amar
aina koletet ba'inan ziknei ha'ir, that's the verse in יהושע, Yehoshua, it
mentions the elders. וליכא, v'leka, and you don't have it. ומאן דאמר
קולטת מצוה בעלמא, u'man d'amar koletet mitzvah b'alma, that's just describing the
ideal, but it's not really describing what is absolutely necessary. It's not
מעכב me'akev as we would say. עיר שאין בה זקנים, ir she'ein
ba zekenim, similarly, if the city has no elders, רב אמי ורב
אסי, Rav Ammi v'Rav Assi, same debate. חד אמר נעשה בה בן
סורר ומורה, chad amar na'aseh ba ben sorer u'moreh, a child can
become a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh in such a city.
Fascinating we'd have this in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. וחד אמר לא נעשה בה
בן סורר ומורה, v'chad amar lo na'aseh ba ben sorer u'moreh, can't.
מאן דאמר לא נעשה בן סורר ומורה man d'amar lo na'aseh ben
sorer u'moreh you can't make a child a בן סורר ומורה ben
sorer u'moreh in such a town. בעינן זקני עירו ba'inan ziknei iro
because it says the parents take him to the elders. וליכא. v'leka.
ומאן דאמר נעשה בן סורר ומורה מצוה בעלמא. u'man d'amar na'aseh ben
sorer u'moreh mitzvah b'alma. No, that's just saying that that would be
the best way to do it. But if there are no elders,
you take him to the בית דין beit din of the next
town. They don't need to be the בית דין beit din of
this town. עיר שאין בה זקנים ir she'ein ba zekenim and similarly
if there's no elders, meaning like no בית דין. beit din. רב
אמי ורב אסי. Rav Ammi v'Rav Assi. חד אמר מביאה עגלה ערופה.
chad amar mevi'ah eglah arufah. If there's a dead body, you know,
a suspicious death outside the city, they'll, so if, and it says
that the elders come, you know, and they make this whole declaration
and they lead the whole ritual of the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah,
but one says even without elders you can do it. וחד אמר
אינה מביאה עגלה ערופה. v'chad amar ainah mevi'ah eglah arufah. I don't
know who would do it. You'd appoint some, I don't know, you
know, some lay people as leaders or something, I don't know. מאן
דאמר אינה מביאה עגלה ערופה, man d'amar ainah mevi'ah eglah arufah, it
doesn't bring it. בעינן זקני העיר והאי וליכא. ba'inan ziknei ha'ir v'ha'i
v'leka. Makes a lot of sense, there in particular, right? Because there
it's like it's about the city taking responsibility. It's one thing by
the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh you say okay, go to
the בית דין beit din in the next town. But
here the whole point is the city takes responsibility and the whole
ritual is with the זקנים. zekenim. So you know, who else is
going to do it? Do they say, you know, presumably some lay
leader or something? ומאן דאמר מביאה עגלה ערופה מצוה בעלמא, u'man d'amar
mevi'ah eglah arufah mitzvah b'alma, סתם stahm a mitzvah. Now תוספות Tosafot
says, what do you mean מצוה בעלמא? mitzvah b'alma? There's a גמרא
Gemara that says that if you have surrounding towns and, and the
closest one doesn't have elders and a further town has elders, it's
the further town that has the elders that does the עגלה ערופה.
eglah arufah. So clearly you need elders. So תוספות Tosafot says, no,
that's just when you can choose. If you can choose between a
town that has elders and one that doesn't, you give the responsibility,
the ritual to the town that does, although they might not be
the responsible town. But if all the surrounding towns don't have elders,
then you go forth with the ritual without the elders. Okay. אמר
רבי חמא בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chama bar Hanina, מפני מה נאמרה
פרשת רוצחים בלשון עזה? mipnei mah ne'emra parashat rotzchim b'lashon azah? Why
when it says in יהושע, Yehoshua, top of י"א עמוד א', yud
aleph amud aleph, the story about the רוצחים? rotzchim? About the רוצח,
rotzeach, right? About the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, does it speak in
a harsh language? A harsh language is because in all of ספר
יהושע sefer Yehoshua among God speaks to יהושע, Yehoshua, it says ויאמר,
Vayomer, God said. But when it speaks about this issue, it says
וידבר, Vayedaber, God spoke. And I mean in like just hearing the,
you know, the way the word sounds, d-b-r, what are those called?
Guturals? Not guturals. Buh, buh, whatever. What? Something. Anyway, you hear it's
the harder word. Anyway, and חז"ל Chazal understood that it always meant
a harsher form of speech. Why is it? דכתיב וידבר ה' אל
יהושע לאמר. Dichshiv, Vayedaber Hashem el Yehoshua leimor. It says look how
many times it says the word דבר. daber. Nowhere else in יהושע.
Yehoshua. דבר אל בני ישראל לאמר תנו לכם את ערי המקלט אשר
דברתי אליכם. daber el bnei Yisrael leimor tnu lachem et arei hamiklat
asher dibarti aleichem. דבר, דבר, דבר. diber, diber, diber. Now of course
the first answer which I think is a very good פשט pshat
answer, מפני שהיא תורה, mipnei shehi Torah, because you're doing a מצוה
mitzvah in the
תורה, Torah, right? וידבר ה'... Vayedaber Hashem... is classically evokes וידבר השם
אל משה לאמר, Vayedaber Hashem el Moshe lemor, right? ואשר דיבר אל
בני ישראל אשר דברתי. ve'asher diber el B'nei Yisrael asher dibarti. So
it's evoking the fact that this is a fulfillment of the mitzvah
of the Torah. Now the harshness might be because like you know
he really wants to make sure that he takes it seriously or
that he's really on top of it. Okay?
It's very weighty. מפני שהן של תורה. mipnei shehein shel Torah. למימר
דכל דיבור לשון קשה? leimar dechol dibur lashon kasheh? Are you telling
me every time it says וידבר vayedaber it's harsh? הין, hin, כדכתיב,
kedichtiv, דיבר האיש אדוני הארץ אתנו קשות. diber ha'ish adonei ha'aretz itanu
kashot. The man, the head of the land, Joseph spoke with us
harshly. והתניא, vehatanya, נדברו, nidberu,
אז נדברו יראי השם, az nidberu yirei Hashem, right? ואין נדברו אלא
לשון נחת. ve'ein nidberu ela lashon nachat. That means pleasantly. וכן הוא
אומר, vechein hu omer, ידבר עמים תחתינו, yadber amim tachteinu, to lead
nations, so to lead you know under us, so it's a nice,
a pleasant, it's being led.
Oh sorry, that's not a pleasant thing.
Yeah, so the context of תחתינו tachteinu is not pleasant but ידבר
yadber is. What can I say? I don't want to debate it.
אלא, ela, so the Gemara says, דיבור לחוד ידבר לחוד. dibur lachud
yadber lachud. No, דיבור, dibur, speech, is harsh, ידבר, yadber, to lead,
might be more pleasant. Anyway, פליגי בה רב יהודה ורבנן. pligi bah
Rav Yehuda veRabanan. חד אמר מפני ששיחם. chad amar mipnei sheshicham. No,
the reason is the harshness is not because it's biblical and it's
weighty, but because Joshua tarried in fulfilling the mitzvah, so God was
angry with Yehoshua. וחד אמר מפני שהן של תורה, vechad amar mipnei
shehein shel Torah, what we said before, because it's biblical. Okay. ויכתוב
יהושע. vayichtov Yehoshua. Now since we're talking about Yehoshua let's talk about
another question about pesukim in Yehoshua, which also connects to ערי מקלט.
arei miklat. ויכתוב יהושע את הדברים האלה בספר תורת אלהים. vayichtov Yehoshua
et hadevarim ha'eleh besefer Torat Elohim. Yehoshua wrote these words, again notice
the word דברים, devarim, in the book of the Torah of God.
So it sounds like the Sefer Torah. So פליגי בה רב יהודה
ורב נחמיה. pligi bah Rav Yehuda veRav Nechemiah. חד אמר שמנה פסוקים.
chad amar shemoneh pesukim. So this is, wait, the last eight pesukim
of the Torah, where we had a debate in בבא בתרא Bava
Batra whether Moshe wrote them or Yehoshua wrote them, because who wrote
from the time it says Moshe died? Did Moshe write 'Moshe died'?
And the last eight pesukim in the Torah? So there's an opinion
that Yehoshua wrote them. So we're tying it into a pasuk in
Yehoshua that says that Yehoshua wrote words in the ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. So what better words could those refer to than the last
eight pesukim of the Torah in דברים? Devarim? Oh also, הדברים. hadevarim.
I wasn't thinking about that, but also in ספר דברים, Sefer Devarim,
right, right, אלה הדברים. eleh hadevarim. You're right, it's ספר דברים. Sefer
Devarim. I wasn't even thinking about that. So it's perfect. It ties
it all in a nice little bow. וחד אמר, vechad amar, no,
וחד אמר ערי מקלט. vechad amar arei miklat. It doesn't mean that
he wrote, no it doesn't mean he wrote the parsha of ערי
מקלט. arei miklat. If you look at רש״י Rashi it says וחד
אמר פרשת ערי מקלט הוא אומר שכתובה... vechad amar parshat arei miklat
hu omer sheketuvah... wait a minute... וחד אמר פרשת ערי מקלט הוא
אומר שכתובה בספר יהושע. vechad amar parshat arei miklat hu omer sheketuvah
besefer Yehoshua. I think רש״י Rashi is saying, I think רש״י Rashi
is saying that the ספר תורת אלהים Sefer Torat Elohim is not
referring to the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, it's referring to ספר יהושע.
Sefer Yehoshua. Okay? That's the way I'm reading רש״י. Rashi. I don't
think we're saying that Yehoshua went back and wrote ערי מקלט arei
miklat in the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. We're saying that Yehoshua went
back, right, רש״י Rashi says שכתובה בספר יהושע, sheketuvah besefer Yehoshua, the
ספר תורת אלהים Sefer Torat Elohim here is יהושע, Yehoshua, it's not
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah of משה. Moshe. Okay. Now, בשלמא למאן
דאמר שמנה פסוקים היינו דכתיב בספר תורת אלהים. bishlama leman de'amar shemoneh
pesukim hainu dichtiv besefer Torat Elohim. Oh yeah it's right in the
גמרא. Gemara. היינו דכתיב בספר תורת אלהים, hainu dichtiv besefer Torat Elohim,
that's the ספר תורה Sefer Torah of God, that's תורת משה, Torat
Moshe, what we call the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. אלא למאן דאמר
ערי מקלט מאי בספר תורת אלהים? ela leman de'amar arei miklat mai
besefer Torat Elohim? What does it mean ספר תורת אלהים Sefer Torat
Elohim if it was only the book of יהושע Yehoshua that he
wrote it? הכי קאמר ויכתוב יהושע בספרו את הדברים האלה הכתובים בספר
תורת אלהים. hachi ka'amar vayichtov Yehoshua besifro et hadevarim ha'eleh haktuvim besefer
Torat Elohim. He wrote the words that are in the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah and he wrote the fulfillment of that command in his
book in ספר יהושע. Sefer Yehoshua. Okay. Now another debate since we
have this idea of debate of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and X,
חד אמר chad amar this and חד אמר chad amar that, we're
going to have a few others not exactly related. ספר שתפרו בפשתן.
sefer shetefaro bepishtan. Let's say you have a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
that you tied the pieces of parchment together with flax instead of
with גידים, gidim, instead of with like sinews, right? They're made from
like intestines or whatever, which is what we normally do. פליגי בה
רב יהודה ורב מאיר.
pligi bah Rav Yehuda
veRav Meir.
It's a debate. חד אמר כשר וחד אמר פסול. chad amar kasher
vechad amar pasul. מאן דאמר פסול דכתיב למען תהיה תורת השם בפיך.
man de'amar pasul dichtiv lema'an tihyeh Torat Hashem beficha. That we learn
that the contents of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah have to be
from things that are kosher to eat. So now of course it's
not that it's not kosher to eat flax, but that sort of
tells you that it's sort of from animal products and kosher animal
products. דאיתקש de'itkash and so we learn that and that also actually
I'm sorry, I said that wrong. That's by תפילין. tefillin. By תפילין
tefillin it says that you have to put on תפילין למען תהיה
תורת השם בפיך. tefillin lema'an tihyeh Torat Hashem beficha. Okay and that
פסוק pasuk that connects תפילין tefillin to תורה, Torah, תורת השם, Torat
Hashem, right, is how we say that all the הלכות halachas that
we know by תפילין tefillin apply by ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So
that's the point. That תורת השם Torat Hashem there connects תפילין tefillin
to ספר תורה Sefer Torah and we know הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai that תפילין tefillin have to be sewn together with with
גידין, gidin, so therefore, here too, we learn that it requires גידין.
gidin. So ואקיש כל התורה כולה לתפילין; V'hikish kol haTorah kulo l'tefillin;
מה תפילין הלכה למשה מסיני לתפורן בגידין, mah tefillin Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai
litforan b'gidin, the same way by תפילין tefillin that's the הלכה halacha
that you use גידין, gidin, אף כל לתפורן בגידין, af kol litforan
b'gidin, the same is true by ספר תורה. sefer Torah. ואידך, V'idach,
and the other says, no, כי איקיש למותר בפיך ולהלכותיו לא איקיש.
ki ikish l'mutar b'ficha u'l'halchotav lo ikish. So no, you only connect
it to the תורה Torah for the דרשה drasha of בפיך. b'ficha.
The בפיך b'ficha דרשה drasha is is that the parchment that you
use has to be from a kosher animal, למותר בפיך, l'mutar b'ficha,
something that you can put in your mouth. So yes, למען תהיה
תורת השם בפיך L'maan tihiye Torat Hashem b'ficha connects תפילין tefillin to
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, but only for the הלכה halacha that the
cloth has to be made from the parchment of a kosher animal.
For other הלכות, halachot, for other details, they are not connected. And
therefore, even though תפילין tefillin requires גידין, gidin, like this cat—you know
what it's called—sinews or whatever, so but a ספר—but a ספר תורה
Torah does not. לא איקיש. Lo ikish. אמר רב חזינא, Amar Rav
Chazina, said רב חזינא, Rav Chazina, לדידי חזי לי תפילין דבי חביבי,
L'didi chazi li tefillin d'bei chavivi, I saw the תפילין tefillin in
my—the house of my beloved, which is רבי חייא—דצפירי בכיטנא, that they
were sewn together with flax. Now that's—nobody says that's okay, because that's—that's
תפילין. tefillin. ולית הלכתא כוותיה, V'leit hilchata k'vateih, that it is not
the הלכה. halacha. Fine, moving on to the next משנה. mishna. אחד
משוח בשמן המשחה ואחד—now Echad mashuach b'shemen hamishcha v'echad we're going to
talk, now that we talked about him getting to the עיר מקלט,
ir miklat, now we're going to talk about the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol dying. Who is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that whose death
frees the—the—the person who went to the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? So
whether it was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who was anointed with
the oil of the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha, which was in the
first בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, ואחד המרובה בבגדים, v'echad hamurubbeh b'v'gadim, or
was the one that his—the way he became כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
was that he wore the special eight garments of the כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, but not with the oil—that happened towards the end of
the first בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, they lost the שמן המשחה, shemen
hamishcha, so the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol only became invested through the
wearing of the garments. ואחד שעבר ממשיחותו, V'echad she'avar mimeshichuto, even somebody
who was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who actually for a period
was retired—or not retired, whatever, like he had some פסול psul and
he couldn't serve and it was יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, maybe he
had had a seminal omission, and somebody else served in his place.
So now you have like a sitting כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and
an ex-כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So even if you're just an ex-כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, that person's death would free the גואל הדם. goel
hadam. מחזירין את הרוצח, Machzirin et harotzeach, it would all bring him
back. רבי יהודה אומר אף משוח מלחמה מחזיר את הרוצח, Rebbi Yehuda
omer af mashuach milchama machzir et harotzeach, even the guy who's anointed
as the כהן Kohen to lead the people into war, because that's,
you know, in some places the תורה sort of speaks—know—talks about it
being anointed and having a lofty status over other כהנים, Kohanim, so
that would include even him. לפיכך, L'fichach, now, whatever—whichever כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol it is, because the death of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
frees this guy, אמותיהם של כהנים מספקות להן מחיה וכסות, imoteihem shel
Kohanim mesafkot lahen michya u'chsut, the mothers of the כהנים גדוליים Kohanim
Gedolim would readily send care packages, you know, to the רוצחים rotzchim
in the ערי מקלט. arei miklat. Okay. Why? כדי שלא יתפללו על
בניהם שימותו, k'dei shelo yitpallelu al b'neihem sheyamutu, says, like, you know,
don't pray for our kids to die. So our son—you know, don't
pray for my son to die because, you know, here you are,
you're waiting to go free, so you're waiting for the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol to die. So the mothers would be very nice to
you, you know, and then you'd say, "Well, if he dies—A, you
just feel maybe gratitude, she gave me all this nice cholent and
food and whatever, now I'm going to wish death on her son?
She's such a lovely woman." Okay, but the other thing is also,
like, if I—maybe now if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, I'll
have to leave this עיר מקלט, ir miklat, I'm going to stop
getting all these care packages, you know. So anyway, so anyway, that's
what they would do. It's also wonderful the sense that, you know,
that there's a sort of belief in the efficacy of prayer, right?
That it's—you know—it's just their concern about the prayers and what the
effect the prayers will have. All right, let's—right? Yes. It is just
amazing, the whole concept from this point. Right? Once they've been in
the עיר מקלט ir miklat and left, does that mean the גואל
הדם goel hadam can't get them anymore? Correct, then they're like protected
like anybody else. That is correct. Okay, מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei
mili? Where is this from? אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, that
all these different—are people are considered כהנים גדוליים, Kohanim Gedolim, that it
includes all these כהנים גדוליים. Kohanim Gedolim. אמר רב כהנא דאמר קרא
וישב בה עד מות הכהן הגדול וכתיב כי בעיר מקלטו ישב עד
מות הכהן הגדול וכתיב ואחרי מות הכהן הגדול, Amar Rav Kahana d'amar
kra v'yashav bah ad mot haKohen haGadol u'chtiv ki b'ir miklato yeshev
ad mot haKohen haGadol u'chtiv v'acharei mot haKohen haGadol, three times it
says the word כהן הגדול, Kohen haGadol, so to include three variations
of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. ולרבי יהודה, U'l'Rebbi Yehuda, who has
a fourth variation, משוח מלחמה, mashuach milchama, כתיב קרא אחרינא לשוב לשבת
בארץ עד מות הכהן. ktiv kra achrina lashuv lashevet ba'aretz ad mot
haKohen. Okay, so it's once again mentions כהן. Kohen. ואידך מדלא כתיב
הגדול, V'idach mid'lo ktiv haGadol, חד מהנהו, chad m'hanehu, it means one
of the three כהנים גדוליים Kohanim Gedolim we mentioned before, it's not
coming to include a fourth variation of who's a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Fine. לפיכך אמותיהם של כהנים, L'fichach imoteihem shel Kohanim, so the
mothers would make all these nice care packages. Or, I mean, if
you have, I guess, you could have—but it's funny it says "the
mothers" because at any one time, I mean, you—the—well, you could have
up to three. You won't have a משוח mashuach and מרובה בבגדים,
murubbeh b'v'gadim, right? In the—you would have but... but you would have
a מרובה בבגדים merubeh bevigadim and you could have an ex כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and you could have a משיח מלחמה. mashiach milchama.
So you could have up to three at any one time. Okay.
Now, טעמא דלא מצלו, taama delo matzlu, so the reason they don't
pray... so the reason that they're not going to that they won't
die is because they're not being prayed that they should die. המצלו
מיתי, Hamatzlu meisi, which means I mean the implication of the Mishna
is, as I said, the efficacy of prayer, that were they to
be praying that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would die, he that
might bring about his death. והכתיב Vehachtiv but why should a prayer
of, you know, that you want some innocent person to die, why
should God listen to that? Okay, maybe we believe in general the
efficacy of prayer, but really? Like here's this כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and because it's not serving your interests and you pray for him
to die, God will listen to that? והכתיב Vehachtiv the verse says
כצפור לנוד כדרור לעוף כן קללת חנם לא תבא Ke-tzippor lanud ke-dror
la'uf ken kilelat chinam lo tavo like a bird, you know, flies
free, כדרור לעוף ke-dror la'uf like the freedom of a bird, כן
קללת חנם לא תבא, ken kilelat chinam lo tavo, a meaningless curse
will not come true. So you're cursing the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
you want him to die, there's no basis for that, why should
God listen to that? אמר ההוא סבא מפירקי דרבא שמיע לי Amar
hahu saba mi-pirkei de-Rava shmi'a li so a certain elder said, I
heard from the yeshiva of רבא Rava the answer to this, שהיה
להם לבקש רחמים על דורם ולא ביקשו. she-hayah lahem leva-kesh rachamim al
doram velo bikshu. The כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim share some of the
guilt. They should have prayed for their generation that, you know, these
types of these types of things shouldn't happen, that people shouldn't accidental
deaths shouldn't happen, which basically means like if something bad happens, you
know, the leaders have some culpability. Now here it's tying it back
into prayer. They should have prayed to God to intervene. I mean,
where's the בחירה חופשית? bechirah chofshit? But you could also say, you
know, they should have done a better
job as religious leaders and spoke to people more about responsibility and
the sanctity of life and care that they had to take in
order to ensure
that these things don't happen. You know, which is so I mean
it is an interesting question, why is the death of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol set this guy free? Like what's the logic between
that? So anyway, here it sort of says, well, maybe they do
have a little bit of culpability in that. Okay. Okay, like we
mentioned the other day about having דוד המלך David Hamelech and having
דוד המלך David Hamelech blamed for not doing... right, דוד המלך David
Hamelech was modeling how people act because right he caused his people—right,
the leader models the right way of acting exactly. ואיכא דמתני כדי
שיתפללו עליהם שלא ימותו. Ve-ika de-matni kidei she-yitpalalu aleihem shelo yamutu. Now
some have the version in the משנה Mishna different. Not that they
shouldn't pray that their kids should die, but כדי שיתפללו עליהם שלא
ימותו kidei she-yitpalalu aleihem shelo yamutu the opposite, you're asking them to
pray that their kids should live, that's a big ask. Okay. But
so now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that's even worse. טעמא
דמצלו, Taama de-matzlu, so the reason the כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim aren't
dying right now is because these רוצחים rotzhim are praying for them
to live. לא מצלו Lo matzlu the implication would be if they
wouldn't actively be praying for them to live, so ימותו? yamutu? The
כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim would die? מאי הוה ליה למיעבד? Mai hava
lei lemievad? Why should the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol be deserving of
death? So הכא אמרינן, Hacha amrinan, so here we say and this
is part of sharpening the question, here in בבל Bavel the way
we express the irony of such a situation is by saying טוביה
חטא וזיגוד מנגד. Tuvyah chata ve-Zigud mingad. טוביה Tuvyah sinned and זיגוד
Zigud gets lashes? Like because ראובן Reuven sinned and שמעון Shimon gets
thrown into jail. So where's the justice in that? Now this is
based on a case where the גמרא Gemara says that טוביה Tuvyah
actually sinned, he committed some sexual sin, and this guy זיגוד Zigud
went to court and said I saw him commit this sin, and
whoever it was, רבא Rava I think or whatever said to him—oh,
רב פפא Rav Papa said to him, רב פפא Rav Papa gave
lashes to the guy who reported on it. So the guy who
got lashes said, what, טוביה Tuvyah sinned and זיגוד Zigud gets lashes?
And he said yes, you're only an עד אחד. ed echad. עד
אחד Ed echad isn't believed. So if you're going around telling people
this guy sinned and it's not a testimony that's believed in court,
you're just spreading לשון הרע. lashon hara. So which is like a
fascinating גמרא. Gemara. But anyway, so where's the justice in that? The
רוצח rotze'ach killed and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is deserving of
death? התם אמרי בי ארץ ישראל Hatam amrei bei Eretz Yisrael here's
the way they phrase the irony of this: שכם נסיב ומבגאי גזיר.
Shechem nasiv u-Mavgai gzir. שכם Shechem married דינה Dinah and מבגאי Mavgai
which somehow means the members of the city or maybe it's a
name of a particular person in the city, he had to get
a ברית מילה? bris milah? Right, that's the story, right? שכם Shechem
makes everybody in the city get a ברית מילה. bris milah. שכם
Shechem got to have sexual relations with this woman he wanted and
I had to get a ברית מילה! bris milah! So where's the
justice? אמר ההוא סבא מפרזיקא מפירקי דרבא שמיע לי Amar hahu saba
mi-Parzika mi-pirkei de-Rava shmi'a li I heard this from the teaching of
רבא Rava שהיה להם לבקש רחמים על דורם ולא ביקשו. she-hayah lahem
leva-kesh rachamim al doram velo bikshu. And this is even heavier than
before. Not just that the prayers will be answered, but that they
start off with a certain deserving of death when murder or even
accidental death occurs under your watch. I mean, you just think about,
you know, things that have happened, you know, recently, of course with
all those horrific shootings or whatever, where's the responsibility of the leaders,
you know? And so it says yeah, you know, they are, you
know, to some degree deserving of death themselves and they have to
be prayed that they don't die. כי הא דהוא גברא דאכליה אריה
בריחוק תלתא
פרסי מיניה דרבי יהושע בן לוי.
Kehadahu gavra dachlei aryeh berichuk tlata
parsi
minei deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. There's a certain person that a lion
attacked and was within
three parsangs, like three kilometers, מיניה דרבי יהושע בן לוי, minei deRabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, ולא
אישתעי אליהו בהדיה
תלתא יומי.
velah ishtayi Eliyahu
bahadei tlata yami.
And as a result, אליהו, Eliyahu, who normally would regularly daily speak
to רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, didn't speak to
him for three days. Because presumably since it happened in his vicinity,
right, it was in the town that רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi had some authority over. So why isn't רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi trying to teach people to make
more protections against the lions and do what is part of his
religious responsibility? Rabbi Luft told me that on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
the rabbi of his שול shul got up and for his main
דרשה drasha on יום כיפור Yom Kippur says, everybody needs to make
sure that the batteries in their smoke detectors are still working. Which
is like really interesting, if I'm the rabbi, I have responsibility for
the safety of my community. So anyway, so how did this lion
attack this guy? What were you doing to make sure those things
don't happen? אמר רבי יהודה אמר רב קללת חכם אפילו בחינם היא
באה. Amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav kilat chacham afilu bechinam hi ba'ah.
Since we're talking about a curse and a קללת חינם, kilat chinam,
it's the חינם chinam and חכם. chacham. A curse that's for naught,
God doesn't listen to if it's not deserving, but a curse issued
by a חכם, chacham, even בחינם, bechinam, even if it was not
deserving, because a חכם chacham issued it, it's going to come true.
מנלן מאחיתופל? Menalan me'Achitofel? From אחיתופל. Achitofel. בשעה שכרה דוד שיתין. Bish'ah
shekara David Shitin. Famous גמרא Gemara at the time, it also has
a parallel in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, which unfortunately we haven't been learning
these days. At the time when David was digging the foundations of
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, so קפא תהומא. kafa tehoma. He dug
so deep to lay the foundation, not exactly clear why he had
to dig so deep, that he tapped into the underwater depths and
the water started coming up and it was going to flood the
whole world. בעי למשטפיה לעלמא. be'ei le'meshfei le'alma. Oh right, exactly, wants
to touch the תהום. tehom. Exactly. And in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it
says that there's a little piece of pottery on top of a
hole, right, and the pottery said to David, don't remove me, it's
going to and David says, I don't care. Just a crazy story.
Anyway, exactly. So בעי למשטפיה לעלמא, be'ei le'meshfei le'alma, the world was
going to get flooded because he released the power of the underworld
depths. אמר מאן ידע למיכתב שם אחספא ומישדא בתהומא? Amar man yadeia
lichtov shem achaspa u'mishda bitehoma? So David had a solution: I'll write
God's שם shem on a piece of חספא, chaspa, which parallels the
version that he took a חספא chaspa off to remove it. I'll
throw it down, it'll magically find the hole, and because of God's
שם shem on it, it'll seal the hole and then it'll save
it. But in the course of it, God's שם shem will be
erased because the water will wipe it away. What was that case
when they had that, I thought about this גמרא Gemara a lot
when they had that underground oil hole that they couldn't seal up?
Remember that disaster that happened like a few years ago? Exxon, and
they whatever and they couldn't figure out how to get to it
and seal it up? I said they just need that piece of
חספא chaspa from דוד המלך. David HaMelech. Anyway, so דקאי אדוכתיה de'leikum
aducha will stay on top of the hole. ליכא דאמר ליה מידי.
Leka de'amar lei mida. Nobody could give him an answer. אמר כל
היודע דבר זה ואינו אומרו יחנק בגרונו. Amar kol hayodeia davar zeh
ve'eino omro yechanek bigrono. If anybody knows this and isn't going to
come forward and say it, let him be choked in his throat.
נשא אחיתופל קל וחומר בעצמו. Nasach Achitofel kal vachomer be'atzmo. So אחיתופל
Achitofel thought, let me think about this. So he made a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. אמר ומה לעשות שלום בין איש לאשתו אמרה תורה
שמי שנכתב בקדושה ימחה על המים. Amar umah la'asot shalom bein ish
le'ishto amrah Torah shemi shehichtav bikedusha yimacheh al hamayim. When to make
peace between husband and wife by case of סוטה, Sotah, God says
you can write my שם shem in קדושה kedusha on a קלף
klaf and directly destroy my שם shem and scrape it into the
water. So לכל העולם כולו לא כל שכן? lechol ha'olam kulo lo
kol sheken? Certainly for the sake of all the world, you should
be able to do this. I mean the question is like with
our halakhic perspective, like what would be the הוה אמינא? hava amina?
It's just a negative prohibition, it's פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, of course
you do it. Like maybe he thought it's part of לא תעשון
כן להשם אלקיכם, Lo ta'asun ken l'Hashem Elokecha, it's sort of like
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it's יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg ve'al ya'avor. I
don't know, anyway it's only a גרמא. grama. Anyway, אמר ליה שרי.
Amar lei shari. It's permissible. כתב שם אחספא, Ketav shem achaspa, so
he wrote the שם shem on a piece of חספא, chaspa, שדא
בתהומא, shadi atehoma, he threw it down, נחת וקם אדוכתיה. nachas ve'kam
aducha. The water went down and it stood on its place. The
other part of the story is said he said fifteen like the
water went so far down and then there was not enough water
in the world because it wasn't close to the surface, and he
had to say the fifteen שיר המעלות Shir HaMa'alot to bring the
water closer to the surface. There's more of this story. Anyway, so
this was the קללת חינם kilat chinam because he only said, if
you don't tell me, and אחיתופל Achitofel told him. It also seems
that אחיתופל Achitofel himself didn't know it until he felt the pressure
to figure it out. It wasn't like he knew it and was
willingly withholding it. So even though it was a קללת חינם, kilat
chinam, דכתיב, dechtiv, nevertheless it says, ואחיתופל ראה כי לא נעשתה עצתו
ויחבש את החמור ויקם וילך אל ביתו אל עירו ויצו אל ביתו
ויחנק. ve'Achitofel ra'ah ki lo na'astah atzato vayehavosh et hachamor vayakam vayelech
el beito el iro vayetzav el beito vayechanak. His counsel was not
followed in terms of the whole thing about the succession and he
went to his city and he gave final instructions and he choked
and died. Seemingly like he did it to himself. Anyway, אמר רבי
אבהו קללת חכם אפילו על תנאי היא באה. Amar Rabbi Abahu kilat
chacham afilu al tnai hi ba'ah. It comes even on a condition,
well that's sort of the case of דוד. David. if you know
and don't tell.
מנלן? Menallan? מאלי. Me'Eli.
דקאמר ליה אלי לשמואל, Dek'amar lei Eli l'Shmuel, Eli said
to Shmuel כה יעשה לך
אלקים וכה יוסיף,
Koh ya'aseh
lecha
Elokim vechoh yosif, so should God do to you and so should
God increase אם תכחד ממני דבר, Im techached mimeni davar, if you
withhold from me this thing. And then Shmuel told him what he
wanted to know. So אע"ג דכתיב Af al gav dechtiv ויגד לו
שמואל את כל הדברים vayaged lo Shmuel et kol hadevarim ולא כחד
ממנו, velo kiched mimenu, that Shmuel told him and did not hold
it back, so the curse should not have been fulfilled. אפילו הכי
כתיב, Afilu hachi ktiv, but it says by Shmuel ולא הלכו בניו
בדרכיו, velo halchu vanav bidrachav, Shmuel's children did not follow his ways
and they took bribes, and that very much parallels what happened to
Eli's children. Eli's children also abused their authority and they took bribes
and so on. Okay, so when Eli said to Shmuel, God should
do to you, the implication was do to you like what happened
to me, you should also have kids that don't follow your way.
And even though it was on a condition, nevertheless it came true.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, נידוי על
תנאי, Niduy al tnai, which just shows how careful you have to
be about your words. נידוי על תנאי, Niduy al tnai, putting somebody
in חרם cherem on a תנאי, tnai, צריך הפרה. tzarich hafara. Even
though it's on a תנאי, tnai, you need to release the חרם,
cherem, the נידוי, niduy, even if the תנאי tnai was not satisfied.
מנלן? מיהודה. Menallan? MiYehuda. By Yehuda דכתיב dechtiv אם לא הביאותיו אליך
והצגתיו לפניך וחטאתי לאבי כל הימים, Im lo hevi'otiv eleicha vehitzagtiv lefaneicha
vechatati l'avi kol hayamim, when he says by Binyamin, right, if I
don't bring Binyamin back to you, I will sin to you the
whole day. So that's considered like נידוי, niduy, to be considered to
be outcast and a sinner, right? So he's accepting it's read as
accepting a חרם cherem on himself, but only if he doesn't produce
Binyamin. Okay, now if you think about it, here's a question. Did
Yehuda fulfill that? In a way Yehuda didn't fulfill that. He never
brought Binyamin back and presented him to Yaakov. Yaakov came down to
מצרים. Mitzrayim. But the גמרא Gemara still understands that look, more or
less he fulfilled it, he ensured the safety of Binyamin. And nevertheless,
how do we know that this curse that he said about himself,
וחטאתי לך כל הימים, vechatati lecha kol hayamim, I'll be considered a
sinner which is read as a חרם, cherem, how do we know
that it took hold? Because it says מנלן דכתיב, Menallan dechtiv, ואמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, v'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani
amar Rabbi Yonatan, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse
יחי ראובן ואל ימות yechi Reuven v'al yamot וזאת ליהודה? vezot li'Yehuda?
What's the juxtaposition when Moshe in the ברכה bracha says let Reuven
live and not die and then he says וזאת ליהודה? vezot li'Yehuda?
Okay, and part of the question is that it doesn't introduce the
ברכה bracha of Yehuda by saying ליהודה אמר. li'Yehuda amar. By all
the other tribes it says ליוסף אמר, l'Yosef amar, לבנימין אמר, l'Vinyamin
amar, but Yehuda just says וזאת ליהודה, vezot li'Yehuda, so it's directly
juxtaposed to that of Reuven. So כל אותן מ"ם שנה שהיו ישראל
במדבר, kol otan mem shanah shehayu Yisrael bamidbar, it was the whole
forty years, עצמותיו של יהודה היו מגולגלים בארון. atzmotav shel Yehuda hayu
megulgallim ba'aron. The bones of Yehuda were rolling around in the ארון,
aron, sort of showing that his soul was not at rest. עד
שאמר משה ביקש עליו רחמים, ad she'amar Moshe bikeish alav rachamim, until
Moshe prayed for him. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono
shel olam, מי גרם לראובן שיודה? mi garam l'Reuven sheyodeh? Who caused
Reuven to admit his sin with, you know, with בלהה? Bilhah? So
that was Yehuda. So it was Yehuda because מיהודה דכתיב miYehuda dechtiv
in the פסוקים, psukim, but they sense since Yehuda made a public
admission of his sin, the reading is that that caused Reuven also
to make a public admission of his sin. So given that Yehuda
did it, וזאת ליהודה, vezot li'Yehuda, is this worthy of Yehuda, the
fate that has occurred to Reuven? So after he said יחי ראובן
ואל ימות, yechi Reuven v'al yamot, Reuven live eternally and Reuven did
תשובה, teshuva, וזאת ליהודה, vezot li'Yehuda, is this the fate that Yehuda
deserves? שמע ה' קול יהודה, Shma Hashem kol Yehuda, God listen to
his voice, allow his soul to find rest. אל אבריה לשפיה. al
evreih l'shafih. So the bones reconnected, they went into their sockets. So
rather than being like the big pile of bones rolling around, you
had a full skeleton now. Okay, so at least his bones were
at rest. והוה קא מעיילי ליה למתיבתא דרקיעא, vehavah ka ma'aylei leh
l'mivta derakia, but they still wouldn't let Yehuda's soul enter into the
ישיבה yeshiva up in heaven. So ואל עמו תביאנו, v'el amo tavi'enu,
so we keep on reading the פסוק, pasuk, bring him to his
nation. So they let him into the ישיבה. yeshiva. לא הוה קא
ידע למישקל ומיטרח בשמעתא, lo havah ka yada l'mishkal umitrad bishme'ata, but
he didn't know how to argue in, you know, have good, you
know, arguments in Talmudic discussion, בהדי רבנן, behadi rabbanan, with the other
rabbis up there in the ישיבה yeshiva in heaven. ידיו רב לו,
yadav rav lo, let his hand be mighty, let him be able
to be, you know, have strength in the sort of in the
Talmudic debate. לא הוה ידע למיפרק קושיא, lo havah yada lemifrak kushya,
fine, he was able to debate well, but he couldn't answer questions,
he couldn't really resolve things. ועזר מצריו תהיה, ve'ezer mizarav tihyeh, let
him have help from his oppressors. Okay, איבעיא להו, iba'aya lehu, now
fine, so that's the end of that story about, you know, that
Yehuda's, and תוספות Tosafot has an important question. תוספות Tosafot says one
minute, because a primary way in the Middle Ages that the rabbinic
leaders got people to follow their edicts was if you don't follow
our edicts you are going to be what? Put in חרם, cherem,
right? Like חרם רבינו גרשום. Cherem Rabbeinu Gershom. But here's the problem,
if I say if you don't do this I'm going to put
you in חרם, cherem, well then everybody's in חרם cherem because, you
know, because even on תנאי tnai it somehow takes effect and has
to be released. So תוספות Tosafot is bothered about that. So תוספות
Tosafot says no, there's a difference. He says Yehuda when he says
if I don't return him to you that wasn't under his control.
And since it wasn't under his control how did he know, right?
יוסף Yosef could whatever, right? So because it wasn't under his control,
it took effect regardless because he was—but as long as the condition
of the חרם cherem is completely something you can control, then it’s
not—it won’t take effect unless you actually satisfy the conditions. Okay? But
this גמרא Gemara creates real important halakhic and authority issues for the
ראשונים Rishonim in the Middle Ages who used a חרם על תנאי
cherem al t'nai as a way of gaining compliance. So just to
see the question in תוספות, Tosafot, he says אפילו על תנאי צריך
הפרה. afilu al t'nai tzarich hafara. יש מדקדקין מכאן דנידויים שלנו, yesh
medakdekin mikan deniduim shelanu, our נידויים, niduim, our חרמים, cheramim, אפילו אותם
שיש להם זמן, afilu otam sheyesh lahem zman, even if the first
of all let's say they're time limits to them, אין חלים הנידויים
מעצמם מספק, ein chalim haniduim me'atzmam misafek, שהרי הכי התנה בדבר שלא
היה בידו לקיים, sheharei hachi hitna bedavar shelo haya beyado lekayem, and
so okay, so it won't work. And then תוספות's Tosafot answer, like
the text is a little bit needs fixing here, but it's basically
is no, הכא התנה בדבר שלא היה בידו לקיים, hacha hitna bedavar
shelo haya beyado lekayem, here יהודה Yehuda couldn't control it, דילמא היה
מעכבו יוסף, dilma haya me'akvo Yosef, או שמת בדרך, o shemet baderech,
ולכך חל מעיקרו גם נידוי על תנאי. ulekach chal me'ikaro gam nidui
al t'nai. That's why it took effect even though it was on
condition, because it wasn't a condition you could control, so it took
effect regardless. אבל שאר תנאים דבידו לקיים, aval shear t'nai'im deveyado lekayem,
but other ones that the person can choose is he going to
do the, you know, do the things that's going to lead to
the חרם, cherem, כגון שמנדין אדם שלא יעשה הדבר, kegon shemenadin adam
shelo ya'aseh hadavar, that you put a person under חרם cherem and
you say if you do so and so then you're going to
be put in חרם. cherem. Okay? ובזו לא חל הנידוי כלל מעיקרו,
uvazu lo chal hanidui klal me'ikaro, that's not going to take effect
from the outset, it'll only take effect when the condition is met,
דכיון דבידו הוא משעת הנידוי אנו יודעים בודאי שלא בדעתו לעשות הדבר,
dekivan deveyado hu mish'at hanidui anu yode'im bevada'i shelo beda'ato la'asot hadavar,
because then we can presume that since he can control it that
he's not he doesn't want to be put in חרם, cherem, so
therefore it's not going to take effect at the beginning, it'll only
take effect if and when he chooses to actually violate the condition.
Okay? But that's very important because that was a major tool that
they used in the Middle Ages. All right, let's finish up here.
So now we have one הלכה halakha question left. איבעיא להו, iba'ya
lehu, they asked the question: במיתת כולן הוא חוזר או דילמא במיתת
אחד מהן? bemititat kulan hu chozer o dilma bemitat echad mehen? When
we said that there are all these כהנים גדולים, Kohanim Gedolim, so
do you need all of them to die if there's a period
when there are multiple כהנים גדולים, Kohanim Gedolim, an ex כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, a sitting כהן גדול—is Kohen Gadol any the death of
any one of them free the free this person or do all
of them have to be die? So תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear it, and you would assume it means any one of
them. תא שמע נגמר דינו בלא כהן גדול אינו יוצא משם לעולם.
ta shema nigmar dino belo Kohen Gadol eino yotze misham le'olam. It
says if somebody's rule is passed without a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
he's never freed. Now why not? So there's not a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, but what about the other כהנים גדולים, Kohanim Gedolim, why
wouldn't they free him? So that's not a question. ואי מיתו הא
הדרי בהדי הני, ve'ee mitu ha hadri behadi hanei, why isn't he
freed with the other כהנים גדולים? Kohanim Gedolim? So it gives the
answer: דליכא, delika, no, there aren't other כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gedolim. It's
not all the time that you have multiple כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gedolim.
But when you do have multiple ones, the question is do you
need all of them to die or not. Let's just read the
משנה Mishnah so we can get a little bit closer a little
to where we should be. Okay, משנגמר דינו—this mishenigmar dino is the
line we just quoted anyway—מת כהן גדול. met Kohen Gadol. Now if
when does the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol death free the guy? Does
he have to already be in the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? So
the משנה Mishnah says no. Once he once the דין din was
done and בית דין Beit Din פסק paskened and said, fine, you
killed the guy, you're found guilty, but it was בשוגג, beshogeg, you
have to go to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, that's your הלכה.
halakha. By the way, that's interesting that there's a concept of גמר
דין gmar din to go to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, right?
It's not just you run and you're protected; like, this is again
the בית דין Beit Din taking over. The בית דין Beit Din
passes its judgment, its sentencing to you, and it is that you
go to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. So once that גמר דין
gmar din occurred, then the person is liable the עיר מקלט, ir
miklat, then the death of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would free
him. הרי זה אינו גולה אם עד שלא נגמר דינו מת כהן
גדול. harei zeh eino goleh im ad shelo nigmar dino met Kohen
Gadol. But if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died during the proceedings
before the גמר דין, gmar din, ומינו אחר תחתיו, uminu acher tachtav,
but then they created a new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol during the
proceedings, ולאחר מכאן נגמר דינו, ve'le'achar mikan nigmar dino, and then he
had a גמר דין, gmar din, חוזר במיתתו של שני, chozer bemitato
shel sheni, then it's the death of the second one. Okay? So
as long as there is a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol when his
גמר דין gmar din occurs, so at the moment of his גמר
דין gmar din you look who the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is
and when that כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies he goes free. Now
what if there's no sitting, no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol at the
moment of גמר דין? gmar din? Okay? So נגמר דינו בלא כהן
גדול, nigmar dino belo Kohen Gadol, so this is the one case
where, right, which we don't know if there's no sitting כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. וההורג כהן גדול, ve'hahoreg Kohen Gadol, now not only that,
let's say somebody kills a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay? And then
by the time of his גמר דין gmar din there's a new
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay? So כהן גדול שהרג, Kohen Gadol she'harag,
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol committed a murder and at the time
of his גמר דין gmar din there's a new כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. All those three cases אינו יוצא משם לעולם, eino yotze misham
le'olam, they never go free. So the last two you sort of
understand, right? But anyway, but the first one was the end of
the point we made before, that it's the death of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol who is around at the moment of גמר דין,
gmar din, and if by pure by luck happens or chance happens
that there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol around at the moment of
גמר דין, gmar din, then you don't have the conditions necessary for
the. ever going free. Okay, the אינו יוצא eino yotzei now, when
he says he can't leave, going back to being in the עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, he can't leave לא לעדות מצוה, lo l'eidus mitzvah,
not to give testimony even that's an even that's for the sake
of a מצוה, mitzvah, ולא לעדות ממון v'lo l'eidus mamon or testimony
for a monetary dispute, ולא לעדות נפשות v'lo l'eidus nefashos or testimony
even for capital crime. Now the question is why maybe בית דין
beis din should go there and you know and and have the
court case there to receive his testimony. But regardless, he can't go
out for any reason. ואפילו שישראל צריכים לו, v'afilu she'yisroel tzrichim lo,
even if he's needed to serve a public service, ואפילו שר צבא
ישראל כיואב בן צרויה, v'afilu sar tzva yisroel k'yoav ben tzeruyah, they're
at war and they need him as a to head an army.
Now of course that's a real big question, right? Because okay, there's
a negative prohibition of not leaving, but like what happens to פיקוח
נפש, pikuach nefash, like the discussion earlier, right? You have a war,
you're the security, I mean that's a very strange הלכה. halakha. משום
לא לעולם mishum lo l'olam שנאמר אשר נס שמה, shene'emar asher nas
shama, there. שם תהא דירתו,
sham tehei
diraso, there he
must remain. שם
תהא מיתתו,
sham tehei
misaso, there he
must die, assuming the
כהן גדול kohen gadol doesn't die first. שם תהא
קבורתו, sham tei k'vuraso, there
he shall
be buried. Just now
last point,
כשם שעיר קולטת כך
תחומה קולטת. k'shem she'ir koletes kach techuma koletes. So
running
in your way running
there
we
discussed whether you'd
be protected, but but at
the city itself
we say
not only the
city, but its environs.
Now what
defines the
edge the scope of its
environs?
רוצח שיצא חוץ לתחום retze'ach she'yatza chutz l'tchum and it
means the 2,000 אמות, amos, that's
the תחום tchum of
שבת. Shabbos. רוצח שיצא חוץ
לתחום ומצאו גואל
הדם. retze'ach she'yatza chutz l'tchum umatzo go'el hadam.
Now
finally the question, there he is, he's exposed, he's out of the
city, he's not protected, the גואל הדם, go'el hadam, what is the
i- we know the גואל הדם go'el hadam is not liable for
killing him, okay, should he kill him or shouldn't he kill him?
So רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר מצוה ביד גואל הדם. Rebbi Yosei HaGlili
omer mitzvah b'yad go'el hadam. There's a מצוה mitzvah in the hand
of the גואל הדם, go'el hadam, the גואל הדם go'el hadam should
kill him actually if he goes outside of the עיר מקלט. ir
miklat. ורשות ביד כל אדם urshus b'yad kol adam and any normal
person is allowed to kill him. Okay, so רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei
it's really very strange, I mean at the end of the guy
this guy did בשוגג, b'shogeg, but now keep the guy in the
עיר מקלט, ir miklat, so you could read רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei
maybe less that the guy is deserving of death and more that
he's he must stay in the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, like he
has an obligation to stay, so if he's really his life is
at serious risk when he leaves, this is going to keep him
in the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, but it still it sounds more
than that and it's very it's troublesome, right? He killed בשוגג, b'shogeg,
why is there a
מצוה ביד גואל הדם? mitzvah b'yad go'el hadam? רבי עקיבא אומר רשות
ביד גואל הדם וכל אדם חייבין עליו. Rebbi Akiva omer reshus b'yad
go'el hadam v'chol adam chayavin alav. Now here's a question how to
read the last line of the משנה. mishna. No, the גואל הדם
go'el hadam does not have a מצוה. mitzvah. Maybe the Torah allows
it and that's you know I would think the פשט p'shat of
the Torah is רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva not just because of my
own you know ethical instincts, i- it seems like the פסוקים psukim
are saying this. They don't want the גואל הדם go'el hadam to
kill him, right? As the פסוקים psukim seem to be saying. So
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says fine, they will not hold him liable,
the גואל הדם, go'el hadam, that'll keep the guy in the עיר
מקלט ir miklat and maybe the Torah can't totally eradicate these elements
of vigilante justice so it has to tolerate it to a small
degree, okay, but it's only a רשות, reshus, there's no purpose, there's
no point, there's no מצוה mitzvah to kill him, and let's say
somebody not the גואל הדם go'el hadam kills him, so there's two
ways to read the last line in the משנה. mishna. One is
any other person who kills the- who kills him is liable, has
committed murder, that's our version, but some have the גרסא girsa אין
חייבין עליו, ein chayavin alav, that everybody else doesn't have a right-
doesn't have permission to kill to- to kill him, but if they
did, it would not be considered murder. Okay, so that also I
think remains troubling to think about that. Okay, but so this end
is a very fascinating about this issue about how much is the
Torah really against this vigilante justice and just tolerating it in small
degrees and how much is it actually saying actually there's some value
to this and there remains some מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so we'll end
with this and continue with the גמרא gemara tomorrow.